hello Daniel
hi Adam how are you
I'm doing okay how are you doing
yeah not too bad uh I mean semesters are
full flow so essentially everything has
to pass through a bottleneck and that's
me
um not everything of course but all my
duties basically I'm the bottleneck for
them everything waits for me to process
them
and that sounds rough actually to
have so much depend on
a pinch point and where that pinch point
is you
well the problem is really that
um it takes a conference resistance
right so uh work is a bit like like a
liquid it moves through the pipes and
then finds a spot where um where it
basically um
is being can pass through and um I I
know that some people actually have this
trick of actually dropping stuff or not
doing stuff and so on and work
automatically then gets re-rooted right
so they don't get less work to do
um but I can't do that
huh
so
bottlenecks
will
in terms of I suppose like a like a
historicity about them
Paths of least resistance if there's
some sort of
topology describing the Dynamics of
what's happening for any system
you'll tend to get
so where will you get like the maximal
flows like where will you get like the
or the the least resisted ones at least
where do you get bottlenecks
where do
yeah that's interesting I mean of course
um depends on on what you talk if you
talk about material bottlenecks I mean a
lot of that is known right there there's
various um Min Cut Max cut algorithms
where you say okay this is the critical
path
for the system uh if you cut that then
the flow really collapses others are not
so much so think of it as a with our
blood vessels think of material flows
think of for example War um War
economies more economies you basically
try to create a system that's not can
cannot be easily disrupted
okay and um living organisms are
a lot like that I do think that's also
part of the philosophy of of talents of
different agility agenda so if you
disrupt the system again and again and
again the system blinds essentially
to embrace the disruptions as a way to
find out ah
this is this is a weak point of my
system okay
and that means that you basically learn
to avoid bottlenecks if possible however
the system is left alone
um and very very robust so you you know
that the system is going to be left
alone and protected and everything you
kind of what you can't afford to have
bottlenecks you can you can bottlenecks
are simply
allow you specialization I mean look at
for example the queen in a termite or ad
Colony that's a bottleneck you kill the
queen you kill the colony in a way
I mean probably not in all species
because then if you kill a queen another
queen will be will be emerging but
essentially the queen is a bottle the
queen is the part through which the um
generational turnover of that Colony
flows
so
um The Queen Is heavily protected so if
you have a bottleneck
then you essentially mean means you can
afford the bottleneck because everything
passes through that and you protect it
you optimize it maybe you improve it and
this is this is basically when you have
bottleneck if you have a highly
disrupted system system that has
constantly to find ways to
respond to disruption
I would claim you will not get
bottlenecks or at least not
um prominent ones
with the
queen of a new Social in psychology
I'm thinking of was it
Anthony zader was talking about I think
like um
genetic inheritance as entailing a kind
of like Auto encoding because of like
you have to make it to the next
Generation you have to pass through this
dimensionality reducer
um and so in this case like the queen of
all reproduction of for the colonies
contingent her she would be this
bottleneck for inheritance but then
she then makes for uh
I guess both uh uh was it a highly
controllable would you uh I think he
said the conservation of misery
and that she would create like a
vulnerability for the system and that
like you now have to expend resources to
protect the queen
um because
if she's gone to college in that case
this is this is related also to the bow
tie
um uh principle that uh John Doyle
talked about I think I mentioned it in
one of earlier sessions
um I just realized that this is a very
similar principle right
um and I completely agree with the auto
and Cooperative I I don't remember who
where I saw that for the first time but
I really do agree that one of the
probably one of the reasons why the
genetic bottleneck actually so effective
is because it's gone from the auto
encoding again and again and again and
again and Link accounting codes only the
part that needs to be Auto encoded the
rest is you know you just grab it from
the environment you do morphogenesis you
do embryogenesis you you do all the
concrete adaptations to the concrete
environment and forget about everything
else everything else is just sent
through the bottom
but of course the genetic bottleneck is
not really so much a bottleneck because
it's very distributed so there's
something very interesting about it
compared to the to the other one in the
sense that yes there's a bottleneck in a
way
that you only send very little data to
the next environment but this data is
highly holographic so it's highly
distributed through the population and
through speciation
it's distributed in space for
individuals and it's distributed in
quality or character because you have
different species
so um
so there is an interesting
way this bottle like kind of evades
their sensitivity
of being a single bottleneck which can
be easily attacked so instead of you
don't have to protect the bottleneck
anymore because there are
bottlenecks yes but there are so many of
them
and across many dimensions
foreign
insect Colony like
so if the queen dies will there be some
sort of like inhibition of like sexual
maturation and maybe there would be like
like a
waiting uh
waiting for that suppressive signal to
be released and then someone else Rises
to drinks and then suppresses others
then you have the new one so you have
some of that robustness built in by
having uh
uh
a set of potential uh usurper
Replacements you definitely have that
right I I forgot the details now which
which speeches actually exhibit I know
for sure that naked moles have that so
naked moles are actually state-forming
mammals live underground and they have a
queen and the queen is the only fertile
female in The Colony
and she essentially keeps the other
females infertile by bullying them
they're being basically bullied into
um stressed out and they don't don't get
hurt when the queen dies
um then one of the others becomes a
queen
right so we know this this actually
happens
um we I'm relatively sure that things
like that happen in certain bee colonies
um that you might have a journal queen
and the original Queen goes lost or that
she leaves or there are different
mechanisms but again I I'm not an expert
in this field so I don't know exactly
how it is but I completely agree right
if a queen dies The Colony
I mean the colony is not lost but of
course it's costly for the colony
Because unless it's in the cycle it
means that you are essentially now
um thrown back by some time to game
resources
so what would
a few of a system
like a
so there's the extents to which your
bottlenecks could be a unified
concentrated or distributed and so in
this distributed system you're saying
there's like more robustness
um
but
I guess well maybe harder to make this
this whole system pivot because you'd
have to get consensus among the
different bottlenecks that might be
harder not necessarily you get to can
get specific speciation right so if you
have multiple bottlenecks
um for
usually multiple the bottlenecks are
linked to different locations different
locations can be linked to different
niches with different environments
different
uh selection pressures
and so essentially you get out of each
other's quick when they don't they are
just separate by space then you have the
problem of
um fraternal conflicts
because if I mean there's a the saying
that says no
no hatred and no Wars are worse than
fraternal Wars they are the worst wars
because they're very similar they're
basically occupy the same each so
basically
the other one is a direct competitor
to the niche you have it I mean that can
work in positive ways if you have
cooperation it can working on
adversarial ways and when that happens
then then you know it's not a good thing
so it works best if the niche are either
far away from each other either distance
or else in
in um in um
um
Niche relevance or Niche character
so you don't interfere with each other
like the the additive Exclusion
Principle I think that might be the
name for that I think it might be called
the competitive exclusion principle
where it's like yeah you're not going to
have two species similarly adapted for
the same Niche Niche coexisting like
you'll have to have some sort of
species speciation or Extinction like
some one will have to dominate or not if
like
or something
I mean we have seen that the 900 000
humans might might be I mean humans do
have some land that's how
uh DNA
so if the separation has not happened to
long ago
there could be future
so
in terms of
I was wondering
the different kinds of bottlenecks I'm
thinking of both society as a mind in
society of minds but um like
so for instance like you know you could
have like a
governmental structure more like a
monarchy or you can have something
that's more like a Loosely Federated
like assemblage of tribes or you could
have
for an individual like
ongoing debate some you know
around like what it means for a person
to flourish where it's like the is the
self
um serving like a vital role like or as
a controller or
is it um uh
basically uh suppressing the flexibility
and diversity and um openness and
diversity you would have from a person
who is not integrated in that way
according to like the coherent narrative
which can become a kind of I guess I'm
wondering about um
the the the trade-offs the advantages
and disadvantages of the kinds of
bottlenecks for persons and societies
like when do you
so like what kind of like conflict could
you have within itself without some sort
of like rank in order of values or
something like this
well the bottlenecks are not emerging
because uh somebody likes to have them
right they are usually the expression of
some kind of
resource limitation okay so
um uh it's not something you seek but
it's something you find
um as a as a society or organisms
organisms do not
seek bottlenecks but the point is
organisms if left unchecked they will
just exploit whatever is available to
them at some point you end up in a
situation where you are constrained you
can't just do what you want you have a
limited capacity and if you have limited
capacity then
um you end up having to arrange whatever
you're doing into this limited capacity
somehow this creates structure without
constraints or to take up the topic of
today's talk conversation
um if you talk about bottlenecks that
means you have limited capacity
something is limited in capacity
whatever it is energy or information or
whatever it is and that forces structure
upon the system now is it a good thing
well from the perspective of the
individual probably not right the
individual would rather have the full
freedom from the perspective of the
system it creates complexity it creates
that thing the conditions to scale up
perhaps or to make it more robust or to
make it more uh compatible with other
systems or to have some kind of
um
consistency across scales because
otherwise you you can't make the
bottleneck work okay so the the point is
it's like like always right if you're on
your own you you make your own rules
when you live with others and you can
move away from each other you don't have
to worry too much about rules but when
if you live in confined space you have
to find rules or your life will be held
um and once you have rules
these European rules can take very
different
very different character depending on
circumstances but also depending on
History right even in the same
circumstance you can have two very
different histories
um the probably the one of the best
lab for such social experiments is
popular in engineer where you can you
have all these valleys there and
sometimes the values are so well
separated the tribes in that Valley will
never visit the tribe in another Valley
and uh they they may live not far from
each other but they don't attract
and it turns out not only has popular
engineer a huge amount of languages
so I I think I have the number in mind
of 1200 languages
but also extremely different cultures
and we are talking here about the
essentially same or genetically very
similar population
and they they
immigrated to the island early on I mean
the population might be as old as really
40 000 years old
um they immigrated onto the island very
early and and nevertheless they
developed in completely different ways
but inside there are Society they had
these rules and these rules are actually
um
quite characteristic
so the rules themselves
would act as order parameters
but it seems like there's like a kind of
um
I don't know if this is if it's like an
entrainment relationship or maybe
there's you could go they could go
separate with complementarity but like
when there are rules for a group of
people
it seems like this would require the
individual to follow those dorms to be
governable by those rules
there's almost like a chicken egg
problem it seems where it's like it's
like the rules create the like a kind of
like or uh or a bootstrapping into being
um I guess I'm kind of thinking of like
the there's an example you're using
um you mentioned earlier about like
um I think it's like a longbow
manufacturer requiring like basically
like um there'd be people to to create
the demand for it to use it but then
once they're there and then you get a
kind of positive feedback going but
getting it started can be a little bit
tricky
it's uh yes I mean it really depends
right once once you get it started it
may be the discovery it may be the the
economic economic niche that you need
right so if you if uh both are probably
not a good example because they are
relatively easy to manufacture even very
primitive ones and the advantage is
immediately visible so
let's take something
what is it another example I mean a
better example is probably or more and
more an example we chose it more clearly
is electricity or electrical electrical
devices magnets things like that magnets
are known for a long time I mean at
least in China that we're known for a
long time probably even even in other
countries and the the Chinese use them
as compasses but
only when it was discovered that okay
they have an influence on the
electricity okay that's one first thing
and then that was not enough you needed
also to see how to
make this combination actually workable
and then
we lost you at um you're saying talk
about compasses and then uh we needed to
work problem once you have that you
still have the problem that for example
yeah I
um the the transition to electricity
so so you make the transition to magnets
can influence electrical electrical
devices
and now the problem is you know we have
electrical devices but at this stage
it's still
a toy
right now when you learn how magnets can
actually induce electricity
you can build dynamos
and now both Edison and and Westinghouse
understood that
to make dynamos viable you actually have
to create a whole infrastructure
for this to work right so you had to
make the decision okay we have to
distribute the interest it's not like
I'm selling this product that people
will just buy it they will not buy it
without the infrastructure so you will
not buy Dynamo if you can't deliver the
electricity to everybody who needs it
and this is here the the
threshold is very high right so this is
very
um probably one reason why the
Industrial Revolution was so difficult
to achieve the Industrial Revolution was
difficult to achieve because to make
things viable a lot of logistical
problems had to be solved
um anything pre-industrial was much less
depending
on um large scale
Logistics to be available right away
I mean there were examples for
large-scale Logistics which is of course
the Bronze Age trading bronze is trading
with big distances and you traded bronze
or the materials to create problems from
foreign
was a trade area
um but
let's put it this way this is something
that can grow you can imagine that you
know okay how to grow that and then you
discover that you don't have enough tin
or copper but others have and then then
you you scale up from there but there
are things where infrastructure is
is really needed
then then you have to really think about
how to how to scale it up the Romans
were also masters of scaling up there
were masses of scaling up stuff
I think you mentioned um it was like um
during the last conversation about um
like a scientific mindset and running
experiments with kind of factuals and
how
this I think you're saying like it
wasn't quite there even for the Greeks
and the Romans they just got things done
like they just go through some yes they
were just really good at getting things
done yeah yeah they were very practical
they didn't care too much about Theory
um it's very clear that the Romans Roman
science was not if if you read plinyus I
mean it's not
it's nowhere close to what the Greeks
were able to do right so
um the the Romans were practical they've
got things done and whatever was
important to be done they were very very
good at
um so they had attention to detail
definitely I mean their Engineers were
amazing they're they're water Engineers
for example when you get the water from
from dozens of kilometers distance you
have to keep the the slope at a very low
level so you don't get creative
turbulence
um and they've got fresh water in the
cities I mean we did not have anything
like that
uh for centuries afterwards
modern water system I don't know
Byzantium I assume that it will have had
inherited some of the Roman achievements
but essentially it's a Roman achievement
and after after the Roman Empire fell we
essentially wait for the 19th century to
have a proper UI system with a proper
water
water and delivery system
yeah
but but the Romans somehow scaled they
they would I really found very
interesting Sparta supporter was
militarily very successful place but
they couldn't scale the way they were
set up they couldn't scale and
um and the Romans could scale because
they didn't care too much about people
having to be pure Romans it would be
okay okay we accept you as as Roman
allies or auxiliaries and and they scale
I always always joking that
um the reason archaeologists like to dig
out Roman ruins so much is because they
know it's like like you know like a big
fast food chain uh you go to a big fast
food chain I'm not going to name any
names from here somewhere and it will
always offer the more or less say menu
and more or less the same services and
will look almost the same and the chairs
will be the same and you're familiar and
with Roman cities is the same thing no
matter where you go uh how far away from
home you are you always have it you
often have a theater you often have
firms you have avocado
itself is always up look like like a
like a franchise
basically Rome franchise it's City model
and they franchise their military
and the French of the military yes
unfortunately not well enough
that that actually messed it up in the
end but yes
in principle yes
were they the first to create the idea
of I guess I'm thinking so
so like a viking Shield wall seems
analogous like a Roman Phalanx but this
like
formation that if you hold it there's a
hole that's where the cylinder's parts
but you have to be in a certain mindset
to like be able to be disciplined into
holding that line
but this is older this is older we know
that the old Greek the Greeks did that
already
I mean the Greek chocolates uh basically
or even the macedonians later right they
had these Shield walls and you had to
rely I think the shield was in the left
the the spear was on the right and you
had to rely on your right fellow to
protect you
so you trusted your the guy on the right
with your life
yeah if anybody ran away the the wall
would break so you really relied
everybody relied on then they right
right does that have its origins in the
Greeks or is that sort of warfare or an
older idea because that I I think I
think the reason the Greeks were this
absolutely devastating military
Machinery was this that was an
innovation
that was a Greek Innovation I think I
don't think that the you know you have
the battle carrier but that is kind of
dating back probably to the hixels as
far as I can um track it maybe maybe
it's older but but I think the Egyptians
got it from the higgsus
um the didn't have it before the
Persians had it in the battle against
Alexander the Great but the battle
Chariot was more psychological weapon
but not wasn't very effective
it was easily defeated
right
um and Alexander defeated it in the same
way by the way as the Romans would
defeat the elephants of Hannibal later
it's exactly the same trick more or less
right so so but the the battle Shield
wall is actually
uh Greek invention
it gets revived in different ways later
that tertio by the by the Spaniards
and also which is less less well known
the
um
I don't know how it's called
how do you call them The Westerns when
they have the westerns and and
um the Cowboys are being attacked and
they build with a wagon wagons the
building circling the wagons circling
the wagons you know who invented that as
far as I know
the the Bohemians the later checks
um it in fact it was
probably invented during the site were
Wars wars of the precise which is a
Proto proto-protestant
um religious group
which
um thought of the the rulers and it was
a very
today you would call the Civil War
essentially and they didn't developed
that also as a kind of battle strategy
but it was super efficient super
effective
and circling the wagons is very similar
to some extent to the to the shield
walls but super effective if and only if
the you don't have
too many people defecting on creating
that formation otherwise it unravels
yeah but it didn't I mean these people
fought very well I mean I think it was
invented by yamchichko was
um the military leader and he he was
blind as far as I know and he he was
never defeated
I guess I'm wondering about
they're not necessarily incompatible but
they see they feel that way at the
moment um two different way or at least
two different ways of getting
let's say three I'm getting that kind of
sensibility so like one would be of like
you actually are playing out the Richer
rollouts into the future and you can
actually see the consequences of like
the construction forming or not
and so it's like it's almost like
rational self-interest with with
imagination uh just another one of like
um
losing your like having creating a coast
self with the other it's like one's more
like planning and the other is like more
of like an immediate coupling of like we
are one body
and who says it's
mutually exclusive I don't know it feels
different but I don't know why it is
different it is different I agree it's
very different today but they could
actually feed on each other right so you
could imagine that there are these two
two drivers
and they happen to join
for a joint root
this is something that I very much
um very much think uh we totally
underestimate right we always say oh
this is the agent and so on but
um Michael lachman has this idea that
actually individuals
um are
not just individuals
um they basically
focus groups of
traits or focus groups of
call it memes or genes or or entities
that that are kind of working together
for a limited time
when the individual dies
then
they dissipate or they pass in case of
genes or in case of memes they pass on
to other individuals but the individuals
are basically just vessels of these
traits and so I would not be
loath to say yeah there are two effects
here Mutual self-interest based on
future production or simply
[Music]
um
the solving the self because simply
everybody shares the same meaning with
you
which is what for example religions do
that's uh I mean one of the main
arguments of Harari right so religions
is a kind of synchronizing element but
of course you could also say
you have one story or more or less one
narrative and this narrative is
basically
holographically encoded in many entities
and that happens to make the entities
collaborate
not because they want to because they
just simply now
synchronize
as per
nature naturally synchronous as
consequence of that
but for them to synchronize I suppose
so there's some synchronization manifold
describing the
coordination that will happen
where
individuals might
form a larger super individual for some
purpose
the
so what conserves a myth potentially can
serve this sort of mechanism design
function
um
is the idea of Truth one of those myths
that we need but is also very dangerous
like do we need to have some sense of
an overarching narrative to create some
kind of
larger individuality
well
you can live with different truths and
people have done this so right so
um
when people had all these different
peoples and say say in the Fertile
Crescent they had all these different
gods and there was this goal for that
and that's good for that and they were
not identical they were they were
slightly different there were
differences they would fight sometimes
they would not even acknowledge their
own the the mutual existence they were
just there but but they would not
actually consider them part of the part
of their their theologuni sometimes they
would be absorbed we know that for
example Hermes and hamstrings megastos
hemispheres Mega stars as actually
supposedly Greek but actually it's a
Egyptian god deity and it was basically
absorbed into the into the Greek uh
Greek um Pantheon the Romans famously
um identified their gods with a
corresponding Greek gods and the
identification is not always
sometimes it fits
Jupiter and and Jews yes they can be fit
and maybe they are even the same deity
in the Indo-European context but there
are other deities which don't fit and
they don't you you kind of tack them
together but it's not really not really
well founded and there is for example
one one date in Roman
society that the Greeks don't even have
and that yet that date is more important
to some extent than Jupiter itself
himself and that's Terminus
permanence is the god of the
borders
so if you have land borders or you have
a piece of land and you put put the
borders that isn't there is a deity
there there's Romans have that
they already have claims of stakes this
is so very unique where do they get
terminals do they invent him or borrow
well I don't know where the where it
comes from but it is uh Rome deity I
don't think the Greeks have anything
analog nothing like that
it's very clear that the Romans had the
concept of land possession much stronger
than the Greeks had
yeah and um
to correspond to it that is fascinating
yeah and the Divinity is quite quite
high up in the in the ranking I think I
think he's ranking with Jupiter either
together or above him or or I think he's
very highly ranked
there are no mythologies about them
which about Terminus 2 which is kind of
weird because it means that
um you don't joke about land position
right it's like you don't joke about
security when you pass past Security in
the airport you don't make jokes there
this is not something to joke about
um
the so truths
what deities can be very you know
basically overlapping and not not really
messing up but the idea that there is
some coherent story
emerges of course in monotheism uh of
course it also emerges in the view of
the Greeks of the cosmos of the
universal order of the world
and in fact
what does the change it changes a couple
of things in the moment you say there is
this kind of joint
I'll avoid the word Truth for a second
join reality
it's a joint thing that basically decide
this is what we all have in common
several things happen number one it
means we all play on the same playground
yeah we're not like having basic
playgrounds that interact and don't
actually don't actually
um intersect
um there are actually some horror
stories which live on the premise that
you have actually multiple worlds that
they kind of intersect and only
sometimes they they meet and then then
you see spirits and ghosts on the other
side there's a fantastic uh Horror Story
by Elgin on Blackwood
um
the the Willows if you don't know it
it's it's it's it's a really chilling
story absolutely chilling story uh very
well written backwards I think that's
the name yes
otherwise this person was faded to do
what they're doing yeah no I think I
think that this is considered a classic
The Willows is considered one of the
classic horror stories right on the
level of Dracula and and things like
that or or the or the or the monkey's
paw or something it's really classic and
it's chilling it's really I don't
recommend doing reading it in a camping
tour really not
don't read it I can't think to it the
best best to read it when it's lots of
people around you and uh it's it's
bright light daylight the cafe or
something that's probably okay but
otherwise really
anyway so
the the realities multiple realities
suddenly are not multiple realities
anymore they live in the same reality
which is
forces several things it forces order it
forces okay there must be common order
to everybody
we all have to agree on certain
principles that are valid for anyone and
not just you can't just choose mix and
match you can't just ignore each other
in other words in the language that we
used before
you have constrained in the mental space
of what's acceptable
there's a metal space and what you move
and you're basically sharing the space
right so instead of having an airplane
all by yourself where you can just you
know
um lean back and just spread yourself on
the seeds and just ignore what what's
going on around you you're now sitting
very tight with the neighbors in the
same spot in the same airplane and you
have to okay we'll share the we should
we'll share their the
arm rest and I will not lean back too
much and and you basically start having
to negotiate your way around
um on the other hand
um well we do believe when we do science
that the reality is like that it's a
shared reality right so
um you can't just argue reality away and
it's a very interesting story can you
argue reality way at some to some extent
you can you can you know you can get
through life very well being a flight
earther perfectly fine
right and as long as you do not have to
um do
um navigation on the on large distances
you can be a flat earther and live your
life without any problems
so
not that I'm defending that as a
scientific statement but I'm saying you
can decide I'm a flat earther and that
is fine and that that's perfectly well
um you can say
um
for example you can you know if you live
in the US you know exactly what I'm
talking about when I talk about imperial
system right you can live without the
metric system it's perfectly okay to do
that
um in fact
well one of them it was okay until uh um
a couple catastrophes with NASA where
they were having trouble keeping track
of units
wasn't always there were some
externalities
that because they had to talk and then I
think the people who did the used
imperial system were not the Americans
it was the British
I think it was a British that did that
so
in in the moment you have to talk to
others you have to have a joint reality
you have to have a joint reality in
which you operate otherwise you know it
doesn't work
um
but you you have a point okay so one
okay
how long is it convenient to work with
um with imperial system so
if you're a medieval person and all you
do you measure distances with inches
feet yards miles
these are related by integers integer
scalings so I think it's 12 inches is
one one foot three feet is one yard Etc
so these are integer numbers they're not
all consistent but there's always an
integer factor between them same if you
take a liquid arms as a weight or a
liquid ounce as a volume or a liquid or
an ounces of weight they are related by
water as a weight of water so it's a
volume
um area is measured again differently
but the point is and this is very
important and as long as you do not mix
areas volumes
um lengths and these things with each
other
you do not have the need to unify
anything you can talk about engines you
can talk about uh ounces you can talk
about Stones okay ounces and stones are
related because the weight and volume
can be translated into each other very
easily
but otherwise you don't care about it
only in the moment when you know our
Force you do mathematics you start doing
integration measuring the volume of of
objects using lengths that's basically
Kepler has a very nice uh very nice
little uh piece of work where he um
essentially derives at integration rule
for the volume of barrels says okay
there's a barrel and you want to know
how much volume is in the barrel by
three measurements
and he then rewrites the volume of the
snap Barrel just by these three length
measurements so now there's an
integration
the moment you start doing that
you are forced to convert length into
volume measures
the metric system makes sense
although even then like it seems like
what you're describing
it's better than the truth in that it's
like basically a capacity for
ensuring coherence where it's needed and
harmonization among like modes of sense
making and adaptation
but like something like a
I guess
maybe better than the truth something
like um a
semi-sacralized epistemic Commons
something like science like the way we
make like like our Notions about like uh
um
[Music]
was that
simply it's a joint illusion it's a
joint illusion
[Music]
if I have the illusion
um like you have the same illusion we
can agree on the illusion and then we
don't don't fight about it and now we'll
talk about let's talk physical truth
which is probably easiest to have
physical truths
um first of all I don't like the word at
all right so not that I don't like it I
think that it's a dangerous word because
whenever somebody talks about truth
um I get edgy I see red flags all over
the place
um if somebody says they know the truth
but that that's edgy because even as
scientists we don't know the truth what
we do is we try to approach
an abstract truth what doesn't mean
we're approach out that's truth we try
to agree on what will happen in the
physical world if we do certain things
and we try to make
that
find the reaction of the real of the
physical world to what we do we try to
find things that make us all agree on
what's going on there so it's a mixture
of
getting the physical world to do certain
things and us having a model that as
transferable and that everybody agrees
upon as well as possible so that if I do
for example let's take a simple example
if I throw drop a stone the stone drops
and
um then there's a
acceleration you know
um
t-square is how much how much it falls
per per after a given time and you do
the same experiment you get the same
result
um to the Precision that you have then
we kind of agree this is this is kind of
a modern model of what happens but of
course
um then there are refinements this and
that and the various things that are
very specific to your place perhaps the
gravity is slightly different perhaps
you are out in space when things again
work differently and then not you have
to find a theory that explains that so
essentially the truth doesn't actually
exist out there there's something
happening there's some
physical Machinery that does stuff we
have
um a theory that kind of
through which we look at what happens
out there
and if that theory is consistent
across individuals that do the same
experiment then we say okay this is
scientifically
valid Theory and
now we could say well this is the
scientific truth but it's not the truth
because it could be there are some
effects that we have not described with
this Theory and we haven't seen them or
the theory is inconsistent and we have
failed to see that it's inconsistent or
the theory
um
is okay on certain time scales but not
on others Etc et cetera so the concept
of this is a scientific scientific truth
is a very dangerous concept right
um as a you know as a simple
approximation it's okay to say oh this
is the truth scientific truth but it's a
dangerous word to use because people
Pretend This is that this is the
absolute
absolutely Undisputed thing that's going
on and that's usually not the case
it gets worse when you start going to
things softer topics like um
um in biology it has improved but for
example in medical medicine it's already
getting difficult what's the truth
what's the illness of this person
um what do they react to the different
people react to different things in the
same illness right
um
you go to history it gets even worse
right so was
um
an evil emperor was he just maligned by
his contemporaries and the problem is
now everything we know about him was
filtered through his contemporaries so
how do we approach
something that if we were to live in
Roman times and would see what Nero is
doing
would be consistent
with what we think about
I've been wondering about
so it seems like this truth with a
capital T
this could you call it like a kind of
neoplatonism
and like it's like a little bit more of
a Greek notion
but like the Romans they would have more
of this like pragmatic truth but like
they were getting things done and so
they would have basically the truth is
like the shelling point of reality which
is like they're coordinating around what
actually gets these done like I say it's
like this you say it's similar but and
can we come to like functional agreement
but this like
truth to which one would uh bend a knee
and shut down judgment
uh or not shut down judgment but like um
a singular type of truth that that seems
I don't know is that
the Greeks the problem is maybe it
exists right maybe there's some simple
the simple truth that actually exists
um the problem is we will never know we
cannot never we can not ever know
right
um and
the the the the problem is that this is
often used as um you know for example
political argumentation
um because it creates like this Direct
hotline
to the deity
direct hotline the data has told me this
is the truth when that happens
and I just so happen to have the hotline
like yes and and yes and people who has
the phone yeah
yeah I mean
um let's put it this way some people may
have had the hotline I mean Newton and
Gauss and Einstein they probably had a
hotline right or for Neumann
um it's very hard to believe they didn't
but but you know this is this is very
very rare
that's that's it uh I I always like I'm
both very compelled by it and it sits a
little uneasy with me like but
Nietzsche's ad hominem against Socrates
where he says like it was like a
um a Beauty value in culture and out of
a kind of like resentment and a kind of
power grab he created this world of
philosopher Kings and ideal forms where
he could like where his will to power
could be satisfied but like I don't know
how far I want to go that makes me
nervous but this idea though of like
something
tyranny prone
uh and and and a kind of uh even like a
domination impulse being like caught up
within it of what would seem to be just
like oh truth what could be truth
goodness Beauty
careful yeah yeah I mean let's put it
this way I accept it as a as a working
hypothesis I accept it as a tool to
guide thinking
I accept truth as a tool to direct where
do we want to go as a scientist
um scientists often say we're looking
for the truth and I don't think they
mean it in a negative way what they mean
is they try to find this
ground on which everybody can agree
um that
things can be interpreted jointly
interpreted and can be jointly predicted
I would say this is what I would think
is what we understand the scientific
truth very pragmatic right it's it's we
can jointly interpret something and we
can join the prediction
so far I can live with this
what is dangerous is that if that turns
out to be ill-defined and we have seen
that very well actually in the covet
crisis the covet crisis one of the big
problems that science was facing is
Sciences scientists are usually quite
well aware of the uncertainty of
measurement
in topics like physics
um the uncertainty has been
essentially almost squeezed out of the
system I mean it's always there right
but but it's so far away from anything
that's um tangible that people can say
oh gravity gravitational constant at
this location is g equals blah blah blah
blah blah so so many digits you can all
say State them that's almost as good as
truth as long as you don't do cosmology
or something right
um
As you move towards biology
As you move towards medicine Things
become very murky the statistics is
really bad right and one reason it's bad
is not just because
statistics is is hard to do but because
of that that's my personal opinion
though
biology doesn't want to be statistical
in the sense as an organism you want to
be unpredictable you don't want to be
easily clusterable because if you are
easily clusterable some viruses can find
your weak points in fact if organisms
didn't have to procreate it and find a
find a partner to mate they probably
would each of them trying to go in there
their separate Niche and really be
different from others incomparable of
course that's not possible because they
have to you know coordinate if they're
made they have to communicate there are
all these pressures to try to keep them
together but if they could choose they
would be very different
right choose evolutionarily choose
um that's a really interesting tension
so there's a slight tension for
regularity and legibility from
coordinating in certain ways
but if you optimize for that too much
you are now a Sitting Duck for another
uh of
an antagonistic Optimizer exploiting you
the conservation of misery strikes again
exactly yeah you're basically opening
the door to a vector it's a bit like
having all your money in One Bank
right it's again John Doyle's um John
Doyle's um uh bow tie idea in a way in
an abstract way
so what did
what what does it mean to us it means
that if that's true and even if it's not
true but but we know that the statistics
and biology is not good and so there's a
lot of uncertainty with every statement
that people made about covet is going to
do this and it's going to kill that many
people and on this age and this has that
effect it's incredibly difficult to
disentangle
um scientists accept that and they
realize that and they have different
opinions what should be done because the
problem with doing is that doing is a
bottleneck again right so there's a
stuff going on but when you have to make
a decision the decisions are not
arbitrary you can't just create some
kind of big complicated uh super action
decisions actions that you take on a
political level or an individual level
are always low bandwidth processes so
you better invest the bandwidth well so
for example if I say I'm going to do a
lockdown now why I'm going to do the
lockdown in three months
that's a big decision you can't just
undo it this is a decision you make now
or later or you can postpone it but this
decision has every decision
is low bandwidth but very high impact
and
the general public has a problem
understanding that because they are used
to clear
facts and clear decisions usually so
when I'm driving a car I go left I go
right it's not always right there the
prices situations where you don't know
what how to react but most of the time
decisions are simple
simple and clear and and you do this way
or do this way there's a reason why many
companies have all these guidelines and
uprs and and and rules and regulations
so that you don't have to make decisions
the decisions are essentially made for
you because this is a condensed
crystallized
um crystallized experience or um
institutional knowledge
in covet basically we were caught
outside of the Playbook
there was no playbook for code nobody
knew what to do it's entirely true
actually there were several countries
including UK that actually had a
contingency plan but it was not enacted
so the contingency plan was not actually
carried out but this is this is the only
secondary the important part is that the
general Republic was very confused and
then people said oh let's do this let's
do that let's do this let's do that or
the scientists say that no the
scientists say this so the problem is
what's the truth now what is the truth
now the truth or the approximation of
the truth would be
you create
a million clones of planet Earth
and start them at the same point in time
say December 2019 and let them run
and you try out all these things and get
the statistics
then you know what is the best action to
take this is basically what you would do
in reinforcement
the problem is you can't do that if you
don't have that model you don't have the
opportunity you can't just restart the
simulation and you don't know which
factors end up actually affecting the
outcomes if you look at Italy Italy had
a huge number of of covet deaths at the
beginning in bagamo which is a rich area
so that you can't say that these people
don't know don't have a health system
they have a good health system
but but I I don't really know exactly
why why they died and then for example
the UK initially did not have at all any
coverage of this out there fine and then
a month later boom it it exploded so the
question is
um
what are the right things to look at and
different people made different guesses
and people got very angry that
politicians looked so helpless
but the reality was maybe politicians
should just have I mean sometimes
politicians said we'll do that has made
a decision like in New Zealand they
decide okay hard luck though that's what
they did hard knock down they can't
covet out until Omicron
right when Omicron came it was they had
to give up it was not possible anymore
but basically until Army Quran they had
coveted under control
um similar what happened to Spanish Flu
in Samoa you had Western Samoa and you
had American Samoa American Western
Samoa I think had the death rate
something between 20 or 30 percent
in American Samoa they locked down
everything strictly
and they had no deaths of the Spanish
Flu
and these are neighbors okay
so
the concept of Truth here is much more
wobbly because nobody can say what was
the right thing to do we have a computer
to do the rollouts
and we didn't have the
and the credit assignment problem was
too intractable even if we could
and he didn't have the data we didn't we
did not know
um what
what other parameters is this the
contagion by
um people meeting up is it is it a
school was it um touching stuff was it
air I mean we know now that it's mostly
airborne right so the whole disinfection
stuff was probably Overkill but who knew
nobody knew that at that time so people
say oh we should have not no no we did
not know that but it's like we need uh
something like like maybe like a lesser
Roman god like Terminus might be too
much for truth but like I don't know
like what's like a veritas
yeah yeah I think I think the problem
here is really we need to be a little
bit more
modest in our expectations
um we need to accept sometimes you do
not know
sometimes there is an uncertainty
and that is part
of the game
it is not resolvable
and and then you have to ask okay what's
the best I can do with my knowledge and
that opinion can differ especially if
there are different levels of risk
aversions so some people are very
risk-averse
and other people are not and the
question is who's right
maybe none of them I mean it's you climb
mountains you like climb climbing
mountains you know and then free
climbing it's dangerous but you accept
the danger
um you tell me to do that I say no I'm
not going to do that I'm not this is
this is not my level of risk but that's
fine the problem with covet is you
cannot be risk friendly
on your own when you are risk friendly
you involve others and now the question
is where's the balance what's balance to
strike the flat earners Earth areas
there's definitely negative
externalities there for beliefs
like the flat earners earthers it's it
could be just fine like maybe
it doesn't hurt anybody I mean they
don't have to travel to Australia nobody
forces them to travel to Australia like
here there's there's failings as we need
to maintain to we need to hold the line
and we need we need the epistemics to be
conducive to that otherwise
you don't it doesn't work
you don't achieve
the the problem with with the covet is
actually really interesting because I
think that
when you talk about
um I had I had conversations with
various people and they were the people
that for example didn't believe in
vaccination didn't believe in masks and
so on and so on now the point is you
know as long as it just affects them
it's fine right why not the problem is I
remember very distantly when with the
whole covet thing started that people
working for Trump's transport of London
people who work for for the Public
Services the the buses and so on they're
where
I think Sev dozens of them
died in a very short period dozens of
them
and and passengers for example casted at
drivers I mean seriously this this is
clearly it's very clearly not neutral
right it has an effect people are
affected it's not it's not like you can
say okay it doesn't matter
people were affected by this there were
other things like
um nurses and and I talked to I talked
to to to
um to people in the in the health in the
health department basically they just
say I mean people just ignore things or
or claim it's not happening and it is
happening I mean these people work with
that now they're they're of course
nurses say I don't want to be vaccinated
I can I can see the fear of vaccination
some people are sensitive to that some
people may not not feel
um feel that their their body doesn't
react well to vaccinations in general
you know I can't see that one The Mask
thing is a different story sometimes it
felt really like I don't wear the mask
because this is a political statement
not because just it's uncomfortable it's
a political statement it's almost like
smoking his sign no smoking they smoke
right at some point smoking just became
obsolete people just
it was enough you didn't do that you
wouldn't it just it's not it's not
doesn't make you cool it's like uh seat
belts and cars seat belts cars at some
point there was a really big discussion
shall we do that shall we do seat belts
kill people sometimes yes they do
still they save many more people than
they kill
and that that is kind of the the type of
thinking that at some point basically
people just tire off the argument that's
that's what happens so it's not like
they they converge to the truth
they just tire off the argument now if
today I will just invent a case in a
very important paper there is a study
that proves no seat belts actually kill
people more than they help them you know
then people say oh 50 years we did the
wrong thing
right but this is how knowledge works I
don't think this is the case by the way
I have to you know disclaimer yeah I do
believe seat belts really help but I'm
just saying that if we find there's a
reversal of our understanding it's not a
reversal of Truth
it's not that we were lied to either
it was just a collective
of the best knowledge we had at the time
that made us
take action
and sometimes you can refine sometimes
you find okay perhaps vaccination helped
maybe we shouldn't give them to people
who have these these these illnesses
maybe the mask did help didn't help
we don't know and some people say well
the mental illnesses has increased
during lockdown so the lockdown was a
bad idea maybe the lockdown should have
been earlier and then it could have been
spared all together for example if you
had done blocked on at the beginning of
Corona squashed Corona right away nipped
it in but maybe we wouldn't have the
pandemic in the first place
or we would have had vaccinations so
early that it would never have gone to
that level that it went
so we made the concept of
like truth
a very task that's that's strong enough
that we can coordinate around it
but not one that becomes basically uh
inflexible and tyrannical and resistant
to updating
exactly and so it's so
not quite yeah
it's
Carl Sagan's book um uh was it um a
demon Haunted World science is a candle
in the dark
that um gave me a I think that that
replaced religion for me when I was
young and it gave me like uh there was
like enough of a of a sense of like
even like a Holiness about the Endeavor
but like there's a beauty to it but it
was imperfect it was like you're always
wrong you're never you know you're
you're always gonna you know never
assume you're not being fooled in some
ways and
but this like but it's still precious
like you're still seeking to do the best
you can yes that's interesting but it
will always elude you it's just a candle
you know it's
and it is always wrong
I I also think it's probably I know that
Papa meant well
but I'm actually thinking his way of
of saying things is actually too
negative and all saying always wrong is
also too negative
um because it implies oh the scientists
don't know anything that's not entirely
true people live much longer today uh
you can do operations on people
um and save them which would have died
um 100 only 100 years ago you can heal
things that aren't unbelievable you can
extend people's lives by by a lot and
really unbelievable circumstance we can
fly to the moon so I don't think we are
wrong wrong is not not the term I would
choose I would say something else we
should accept that's an impressive
candle that can take you to the Moon
yes that's a big one yes 110 meters as
well yeah
um
and the candle burns from the bottom
very important
um
it is
the decision that we're trying to take
should be
reflecting our very best
approximation
to this
jointly consistent
grounds
that hold up as well as possible to the
Future
doesn't guarantee it's a case but this
is what we want when people say do
something because of an agenda it means
that they're not caring about this
they're caring about creating something
favorable for them they take basically
uh
they are partial they they
are partisan they are partisan and they
decide okay
we have picked this direction
um for our purpose this is what
the say people on the street are afraid
of being taken advantage of
I don't blame them for that right people
are very afraid of being taken advantage
of right sometimes
um they are right evil it's probably
true
um in enough or true it's probably
a good good way of describing the
situation in enough cases that they're
probably right still
I think we need to
keep not just the camel we need to keep
a flag of Truth seeking
brother truth truth seeking up saying we
are trying to find the what's going on
we're trying to be consistent we're
trying to do decisions that are
reflecting your best understanding of
what
what's a good future but of course
different
agents have probably different thinking
of what's good for the future
but that's a different story that in my
opinion is not part of the story of
truth anymore that is part of of the
story of politics
and let's get gets nasty when politics
distorts truth in the service
of partisan agendas
thank you Daniel
thank you
I'm looking forward to next time